Finding Aid for Lenore LaFount Romney Papers 1960-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lenore LaFount Romney Papers 1960-1974, 1962-1970
Romney, Lenore LaFount.
1 oversize volumes
10 linear feet
Civic leader, wife of Michigan governor, George Romney, and Republican candidate for the U.S. Senate in 1970. Correspondence, political background files, speeches, and miscellanea largely concerning election of 1970; and campaign and speech files covering gubernatorial career of George Romney.
852228 Aa 2; AC
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Lenore Romney (donor no. 5424 ) donated her campaign files in 1973-1974. Some of the audio-tapes were transferred over from the George Romney accession (donor no. 4703 ).
The collection is open for research.
Lenore LaFount Romney was born in 1909 in Ogden, Utah. In 1931, she married George Wilcken Romney, who was later to become President of American Motors, Governor of Michigan and Secretary of Housing and Urban Development. A well-respected and admired politician and public figure in her own right, Lenore Romney took an active role in state politics as Michigan's first lady. Both then, and later as wife of a cabinet secretary, she traveled widely, speaking on issues such as poverty, volunteerism, women's rights and the Vietnam War. She announced her candidacy for United States Senator from Michigan in 1969, running against Democratic incumbent Phil Hart. Romney was hampered in her campaign by her unpopular positions--she supported Nixon's stand on the Vietnam War--and her lack of a concrete platform--long on moral positions but short on specifics. At a time when there was just one woman in the U.S. Senate, her being in the race at all raised many eyebrows, especially given her husband's own political career. Many thought that she should let Mr. Romney wear the political hat in the family. Although her moral courage was widely admired, she was soundly defeated in November 1970. After the election, she continued to live in the public eye, speaking out on issues of concern to her, including volunteerism, women's rights, abortion, and the inverse relationship between morality and crime.
The Lenore Romney papers (1960-1974) include correspondence, speeches, and other materials relating to her official role as the wife of Governor George Romney. In addition, there are files that relate to her participation in the political campaigns of her husband and to her own campaign for the U.S. Senate in 1970.
Subjects:
Civic leaders--Michigan.; Governors--Michigan.; Governors' spouses--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Romney, Lenore LaFount.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1970.; Women in politics--Michigan.; Women civic leaders--Michigan.
Subjects - Sound recordings:
Elections--Michigan--1970.; Governors--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Republican Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Romney, Lenore LaFount.
Contributors - Sound recordings:
Romney, George W., 1907-1995.
Genre/Form:
Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1962-June 1965, 26 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1965-May 1967, 31 folders (Box 2)
  - June 1967-April 1968, 25 folders (Box 3)
  - May 1968-November 1968, 12 folders (Box 4)
- County Files (arranged alphabetically)
  - Alcona to Jackson (Box 4)
  - Newaygo to Wayne 1962 (Box 5)
  - Wayne 1963 to Wexford (Box 6)
- Topical Files 1962-1970
  - Cultural Activities (Box 6)
  - Governor's addresses (Box 6)
  - Education (Box 6)
  - Internal (office) papers (Box 6)
  - Japan addresses (Box 6)
  - Mental Health (Box 6)
  - Michigan Ophthalmology Society (Box 6)
  - Michigan Youth Commission (Box 6)
  - Mott Foundation (Box 6)
  - Needs of Children (Box 6)
  - Russia-Yesterday and Today (Box 6)
  - Russell Woods Association (Box 6)
  - Romney-Governor (Box 6)
  - Schedules 1963-1968, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Talking Points (Box 6)
  - T.V. Programs (Box 6)
  - Women's Role (Box 7)
  - World Medical Relief (Box 7)
  - Women for Nixon-Agnew (Box 7)
  - Women for Romney, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Biographical
  - Biographical (Box 7)
  - Genealogical (Box 7)
- Campaign for Senate 1970
  The Campaign for Senate series includes position papers outlining the Romney campaign's platform as well as a well-researched investigation into the record of her opponent, Phil Hart. Included are newspaper clippings collected by the campaign staff for a scrapbook (which apparently was never compiled) detailing the candidate's life during the campaign.
  - Position Papers
    - Abortion (Box 7)
    - Capital Punishment (Box 7)
    - Crime (Box 7)
    - Department of Interior (Box 7)
    - Drugs (Box 7)
    - Economy (Box 7)
    - Education (Box 7)
    - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 7)
    - Farm Problems (Box 7)
    - Federal Assistance Program (Box 7)
    - Foreign Affairs (Box 7)
    - General (Box 7)
    - Population Control (Box 7)
    - Press (Box 7)
    - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 7)
    - Vietnam (Box 7)
    - Voting Age (Box 7)
  - Generic Letter Responses (Box 7)
  - Campaign Staff Lists (Box 7)
  - Press Information Kit (Box 7)
  - Staff Memoranda (Box 7)
  - Hart Record
    - 1965-1970
      - Crime and Lawlessness (Box 7)
    - 91st Congress
      - Overview (Box 7)
      - Subject Analysis (Box 7)
      - Key Votes (Box 7)
      - Legislation (Box 7)
      - Key Bills (Box 7)
      - Committees (Box 7)
  - Clippings
    - January-December 1970, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook concerning senatorial campaign 1970 (Box 7)
    (1 oversize volume, AC, and loose pages)
- Speeches
  - Campaign speeches by issue
    - Aging (Box 7)
    - Consumerism (Box 7)
    - Drugs (Box 7)
    - Economics (Box 7)
    - Environment (Box 7)
    - Farming (Box 7)
    - Flag Day (Box 7)
    - Health Care (Box 7)
    - Housing (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Mormons (Box 7)
    - Set Pieces (Box 7)
    - Volunteers (Box 7)
    - Women (Box 7)
  - Campaign speeches by date
    - 1964-1969 (Box 7)
    - Announcement of Candidacy June 1, 1969 (Box 7)
    - May 1970 (Box 7)
    - June-August 1970 (Box 7)
    - September 1970 (Box 7)
    - October-November 1970 (Box 7)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 7)
- Other Materials
  - WJR Point Of View radio program 1974 (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
  - Clippings
    - 1960-1963 (Box 7)
    - 1964 (Box 7)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 7)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    - Undated (Box 7)
- Audio-tapes
  Recordings of speeches, interviews, and WJR Detroit radio program, "A Visit with Lenore Romney."
  (7" except where indicated)
  - By date
    - LR, Birthday Party, Detroit undated, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR interview 1962, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Royal Oak Republican Women's Club May 1962, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR press conference June 5, 1962, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR interview, WTVB radio, Coldwater July 21, 1962, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech at opening of 17th District Headquarters September 12, 1962, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech October 22, 1962, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
      (also includes speeches by Mrs. John B. Swainson and John F. Kennedy)
    - LR speech, Ionia County Fair August 12, 1962, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Farmers Week, Michigan State University February 1965, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Seventh-Day Adventists, Grand Ledge, Michigan August 3, 1966, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR address, Women's Federation Convention, Kalamazoo, Michigan September 23, 1966, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, International Convention of Christian Business Men's Committee, Detroit, Michigan October 1, 1966, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Dayton County Club, Dayton, Ohio 1967, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Republican Rally 1967, 3-3/4 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, BPOE February 21, 1967, 5" tape; 3.75 ips (Box 8)
    - LR interview, Lou Gordon Show April 16, 1967, 5" tape; 1-7/8 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Holland, Michigan May 17, 1967, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Convention (?) June 23, 1967, 5" tape; 3.75 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Midwest Governor Conference August 1967, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR interview with Bob Grant, KLAC August 3, 1967, 5" tape; 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, South Dakota October 25, 1967, 5" tape; 3.75 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, Kiwanis Club of Danville, Illinois June 6, 1968, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
    - LR speech, St. James Methodist Church, Danville, Illinois June 6, 1968, 7-1/2 ips (Box 8)
  - WJR radio program, "Visit with Lenore Romney"
    (most tapes are 7 inch and 7-1/2 ips)
    - January-April 7,1967, 11 reels (Box 8)
    - April 14, 1967-March 10, 1968, 38 reels (Box 9)
    - March 24, 1968-December 15, 1968, 33 reels (Box 10)